YM/YWHA Arts Council
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
YM/YWHA Arts Council records
1962-2006, bulk 1967-1981
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Young Men's and Young Women's Hebrew Association of Philadelphia. Arts Council
1.2 linear feet
The records of the YM/YWHA Arts Council measure 1.2 linear feet and date from 1962 to 2006, with the bulk of the records dating from 1967 to 1981. This collection documents the activities of the Philadelphia-based arts organization, primarily during the period that Judith Golden was the council chair. Included are administrative records, scattered correspondence, exhibition and program files, and printed material.
Provenance
The YM/YWHA Arts Council records were lent for microfilming in 1986 and subsequently donated with additional unmicrofilmed material in 2010 by Judith Golden, former chairman of the YM/YWHA Arts Council of Philadelphia.
Related Material
Additional YM/YWHA records were donated in 1986 by Acey Wolgin, an early member of the Association. These records were transferred to the vertical file of Smithsonian American Art Museum Library after microfilming, and are available on microfilm reel 4340. Also at the Archives of American Art are the Joan Kron papers, 1959-1971, and the Audrey Sabol papers, 1962-1967. Both collections document their work with the YM/YWHA Arts Council of Philadelphia.
Alternative Forms Available
Portions of the collection are available on 35 mm microfilm reel 3898 at Archives of American Art offices, and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of documents on microfilm does not match the current arrangement of these records.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Historical Note
The YM/YWHA Arts Council was established in 1958 as a volunteer organization dedicated to bringing the visual and performing arts to Philadelpha. Judith Golden was Arts Council Chairman from 1969-1971 and Advisory Co-Chair from 1974-1976.
Scope and Content Note
The records of the YM/YWHA Arts Council measure 1.2 linear feet and date from 1962 to 2006, with the bulk of the records dating from 1967 to 1981. This collection documents the activities of the Philadelphia-based arts organization, primarily during the period that Judith Golden was the council chair. Included are administrative records, scattered correspondence, exhibition and program files, and printed material.
Administrative records include documentation on the Arts Council history, the council manual belonging to Judith Golden, committee member lists, meeting minutes and agendas, and documentation on grants and program funding. Also found are draft letters to members, draft press releases, scattered printed material and correspondence, meeting records, notes, reports, and proposed budgets. Correspondence is from 1969 to 1972 and includes Judith Golden's outgoing and incoming correspondence as Chairman of the Arts Council. Additionally, there is one letter addressed to Golden from 2004.
The exhibition and program files document art exhibitions, theater and dance performances, lectures, and patron events organized by the YM/YWHA Arts Council. Files may include performance agreements, planning documents, correspondence, printed announcements, press releases, and press clippings.
Printed Material consists of numerous brochures and program announcements for events at the YM/YWHA. Also found are magazines and newpaper clippings documenting arts events, scattered press releases, and The Review newsletter, published by the Jewis Ys and Centers of Greater Philadelphia.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as # series:
Series 1: Administrative Records, circa 1966-1981 (Box 1; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1969-1972, 2004 (Box 1; 3 folders)
Series 3: Exhibition and Program Files, 1962-1970s, 2006 (Box 1; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1967-1987 (Box 1-2; 0.4 linear feet)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects-Topical:
Art--Exhibitions--Pennsylvania--Philadelphia; Art centers--Pennsylvania--Philadelphia; Associations, institutions, etc.--Pennsylvania--Philadelphia
Types of Materials:
Drafts (documents); Minutes
Names:
Golden, Judith
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Administrative Records, circa 1966-1981, Series 1:; (Box 1; 0.4 linear feet)
  This series contains administrative records of the YM/YWHA Arts Council maintained by Judith Golden, and primarily documenting the periods that she was Council Chairman or on the advisory committee. Included is documentation on the Arts Council history, the council manual belonging to Golden, committee member lists, meeting minutes and agendas, and documentation on grants and program funding. Also found are two files on the activities of the Poetry Committee. General administrative records include member lists, draft letters to members, draft press releases, scattered printed material and correspondence, meeting records, notes, reports, and proposed budgets.
  - Arts Council History, circa 1968-1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Arts Council Manual, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Arts Council Review Committee, 1968-1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Executive Committee and Board Member Lists, 1966-1970, 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Funds and Grants Information, 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - General Administrative Records, 1967-1969, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - General Administrative Records, 1973-1980, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 8-11)
  - General Administrative Records, "New Arts Council," 1981 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Meeting Agendas and Minutes, 1969-1970, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
  - Membership and Sponsor Materials, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Philadelphia Foundation Grant, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Poetry Committee, 1972-1973, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
  - Photograph of Y Building, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - YM/YWHA Logo, circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Correspondence, 1969-1972, 2004, Series 2:; (Box 1; 3 folders)
  Correspondence is from 1969 to 1972 and includes Judith Golden's outgoing and incoming correspondence as Chairman of the Arts Council. Also included are a few letters written by other committee members. Additionally, there is one letter addressed to Golden from 2004. Researchers should note that additional correspondence is included among the general administrative records in Series 1 and within the exhibition and program files in Series 3.
  - Correspondence, 1969-1972, 2004, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 21-23)
- Exhibition and Program Files, 1962-1970s, 2006, Series 3:; (Box 1; 0.4 linear feet)
  This series contains files on exhibitions and programs held by the YM/YWHA Arts Council. Besides art exhibitions, programs included theater and dance performances, lectures, and patron events. Files may include performance agreements, planning documents, correspondence, printed announcements, press releases, and press clippings. Also found is one file on a 2006 exhibition at the Gershman Y of works by Sam Maitin which was based on a 1972 exhibition of his works organized by the Arts Council.
  Files are arranged chronologically.
  - Proposed Programs, circa 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Film Programs, 1969-1970s (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Art 1963 A New Vocabulary (1962), 1962 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Tom Paine (1968) and La Mama Experimental Theatre Background Information, circa 1968, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 27-28)
  - A Black Quartet (1969), 1969 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - The Hoofers (1969), 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Jerzy Grotowski's Polish Laboratory Theatre (1969), 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - The Making of Arts Council TV Commercials: A Party for Patrons and Sponsors (1969), 1969 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Sculpture to Wear (1969), 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Birgit Cullberg Ballet Theatre (cancelled), 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - First Chamber Dance Company of New York (1970), 1970 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Lottery of Living Experiences Sponsor/Patron Event (1970), 1969-1971, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 36-37)
  - William Kunstler Program (1970), circa 1970, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 38-39)
  - Yvonne Rainer, Performance Demonstration #1 (1970), 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - David Amram: One World of Music (1971), 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Tom Wolfe Program (1971), 1971 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Flying Colors: Sam Maitin's Legacy at the Gershman Y (2006), 1971-1972, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Printed Material, 1967-1987, Series 4:; (Box 1-2; 0.4 linear feet)
  Printed Material consists of numerous brochures and program announcements for events at the YM/YWHA, including calendars of events, performance programs, and general brochures about the Arts Council. Also found are magazines and newpaper clippings documenting arts events, scattered press releases, and The Review newsletter, published by the Jewish Ys and Centers of Greater Philadelphia.
  - Event Brochures and Program Announcements, 1968-1980, (5 folders) (Box 1, Folder 44-48)
  - Magazines, 1968-1987 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - News Clippings, 1967-1980, (8 folders) (Box 2, Folder 2-9)
  - News Clippings, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Press Releases, circa 1970-1975 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - The Review Newsletter, 1969-1976 (Box 2, Folder 12)